<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ELF Lab</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content on ELF Lab</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>New Paper from Chris Hammerly and Minh Nguyen</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/minh&#43;chrispaper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/minh&#43;chrispaper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;ELF Lab members Chris and Minh have published a proceedings paper at the conference &lt;a href=&#34;https://turing.iimas.unam.mx/americasnlp/&#34;&gt;AmericasNLP&lt;/a&gt; on Ojibwe machine translation.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Nguyen, M. Hammerly, C. Silfverberg, M. (2025) A hybrid approach to low-resource machine translation for Ojibwe verbs. &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the 5th Workshop on Natural Language Processing for Indigenous Languages of the Americas (AmericasNLP 2025).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Paper from from ELF members and collaborators</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/naaclpaper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/naaclpaper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;ELF Lab members and collaborators, Shenran Wang, Changbing Yang, Mike Parkhill, Chad Quinn, Jian Zhu, and Chris Hammerly published a paper in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://naacl.org/&#34;&gt;NAACL&lt;/a&gt; proceedings.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Wang, S., Yang, C., Parkhill, M., Quinn, C., Hammerly, C., and Zhu, J. (2025) Developing multilingual speech synthesis system for Ojibwe, Mi’kmaq, and Maliseet. &lt;em&gt;In Proceedings of the 2025 Conference of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (NAACL).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Paper from Viann Sum Yat Chan and Chris Hammerly</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/viann&#43;chrispaper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/viann&#43;chrispaper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;ELF Lab members, Viann and Chris published a paper in the proceedings of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://computel-workshop.org/&#34;&gt;ComputEL-8 Workshop&lt;/a&gt; in Honolulu on an Ojibwe text-to-speech Teacher Workshop&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chan, V. &amp;amp; Hammerly, C. (2025) Evaluating Indigenous language speech synthesis for education: A participatory design workshop on Ojibwe text-to-speech. &lt;em&gt;In Proceedings of the 8th Workshop on the Use of Computational Methods in the Study of Endangered Languages (ComputEL-8).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ELF lab @ LSURC 2025!</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/lsurc/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/lsurc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At the end of February, our Director Dr.Hammerly was invited as a plenary speaker to the Language Sciences Undergraduate Research Conference. This conference run by UBC undergraduates is a celebration of the exciting research done by undergraduates across Canada.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dr. Hammerly was invited to speak on the various projects being developed at ELF Lab relating to technology&amp;rsquo;s role in language revitalization.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Additionally, our undergraduate RA, Hope Trischuk, gave an oral presentation on her work with ELF lab: Assessing Intuitions about Obviation in Learners of Anishinaabemowin.&#xA;For her efforts, she was awarded first place in the Oral Presentation category!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lab Meeting-March 25th</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/labmeetingannouncement1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/labmeetingannouncement1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Next full lab meeting will be on March 25th from 4-5pm in Stores Road Annex Room 5&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Feel free to reach out if you would like to attend and learn more about ELF lab!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/contact/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you have any questions or inquiries about current studies, research, joining our team or anything else related to the lab do not hesitate to reach out via email!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ELF lab email: &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:elf.lab@ubc.ca&#34;&gt;elf.lab@ubc.ca&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Members</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/members/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/members/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;current-members&#34;&gt;Current Members&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;table&gt;&#xA;  &lt;thead&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;          &lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/thead&gt;&#xA;  &lt;tbody&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr. Christopher Hammerly&lt;/strong&gt; is Director of ELF-Lab and an Assistant Professor in the Department of Linguistics at UBC. He is a member (descendent) of the White Earth Nation in Minnesota of mixed Anishinaabe and Norwegian American descent. His work primarily focuses on his ancestral language Anishinaabemowin. He uses a variety of methods to understand the cognitive representations and processes underpinning human knowledge of syntax (sentence structure) and morphology (word structure), including formal theories, fieldwork, computational models, and experimental tasks.&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/ChrisHeadshot.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Chris Hammerly Headshot&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/tbody&gt;&#xA;&lt;/table&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;ma-students&#34;&gt;MA Students&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;table&gt;&#xA;  &lt;thead&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;          &lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/thead&gt;&#xA;  &lt;tbody&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anna Stacey&lt;/strong&gt; is an MA student at UBC Linguistics, where she works on technological developments for Indigenous languages.  She got her BSc in Computer Science and Linguistics from UManitoba in 2022.  Anna has been developing software for ELF Lab as an RA for 2+ years, working on code for eye-tracking experiments (VisualWorldTools) and creating tests for the Ojibwe morphological parser (ParserTools).  She is also involved in fieldwork on Nɬeʔkepmxcín, a Salish language spoken in the Pacific Northwest.  In her free time, she loves heading outside to work on her knowledge of flowers and birds, and making music.&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/AnnaHeadshot.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Anna Stacey Headshot&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marcella Jurotich&lt;/strong&gt; is a first-year master’s student in Linguistics at UBC. Her research interests are in syntax and psycholinguistics, particularly in the interaction between Information Structural elements and syntax and the processing of non-canonical structures. She is excited to be part of the ELF-Lab and to be able to learn more about Anishinaabemowin. In her spare time, she enjoys embroidering, dancing, and playing piano.&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/MarcellaHeadshot.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Marcella Jurotich Headshot&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mila Loginova&lt;/strong&gt; is an MA Linguistics student interested in Indigenous language preservation and documentation. She got her BA in Cognitive Science of Language from McMaster University, where she first encountered Anishinaabemowin and found herself fascinated by the morphology and syntax of the language. In the ELF-lab, she’s one of the people working on the Anishinaabemowin corpus.&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/MilaHeadshot.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Mila Loginova Headshot&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Minh Nguyen&lt;/strong&gt; is a recent graduate of the UBC Master of Data Science -  Computational Linguistics (MDS-CL) program, with a background in Computer Science and Finance. He has a distinct passion for languages and programming. He is involved in exciting projects such as machine translation with the Ojibwe language and data construction. Outside of his professional endeavors, he holds a keen interest in general AI and physics, particularly in quantum physics.&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/MinhHeadshot.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Minh Nguyen Headshot&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/tbody&gt;&#xA;&lt;/table&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cindy Zhang&lt;/strong&gt; is a student in UBC&amp;rsquo;s MDS-CL program, and has been working as a volunteer Research Assistant in our project to build a text-based corpus for Ojibwe. She has focused on text processing for integration into the corpus infrastucture.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/projects/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OjibweMorph: An approachable morphological parser for Ojibwe&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Funding: SSHRC&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Team: Christopher Hammerly, Miikka Silfverberg, Antti Arppe, Nora Livesay, Anna Stacey&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Related Outputs:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Steiner, R. &amp;amp; Hammerly, C. (To Appear) A phonological reanalysis of Ojibwe nominal inflection classes. Papers of the 55th Algonquian Conference.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://christopherhammerly.com/publication/ojibwemorph/OjibweMorph.pdf&#34;&gt;Hammerly, C., Livesay, N., Arppe, A., Stacey, A., &amp;amp; Silfverberg, M. (Submitted) OjibweMorph: An approachable morphological parser for Ojibwe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Hammerly, C., Parkhill, S., Goodyear, L., Silfverberg, S., Quinn, C., &amp;amp; Parkhill, M. (2025) An Automatic Verb Conjugation Tool for Ojibwe. 9th International Conference on Language Documentation and Conservation (ICLDC9). University of Hawai’I at Mānoa.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Creating speech synthesis for Ojibwe, Mi’kmaq, and Maliseet&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
